<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation strange and true, of a ship of Bristol named the Iacob of 120. tunnes, which was about the end of Octob. last 1621. taken by the Turkish pirats of Argier. And how within fiue dayes after, foure English youths did valiantly ouercome 13. of the said Turks, and brought the ship to S. Lucas in Spaine, where they sold nine of the Turks for gally-slaues.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04200</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14322</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119754</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854960</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854960</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20426</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04200)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20426)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1489:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation strange and true, of a ship of Bristol named the Iacob of 120. tunnes, which was about the end of Octob. last 1621. taken by the Turkish pirats of Argier. And how within fiue dayes after, foure English youths did valiantly ouercome 13. of the said Turks, and brought the ship to S. Lucas in Spaine, where they sold nine of the Turks for gally-slaues.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Eliot's Court Press?] for Nathaniel Butter, and are to be sold at his shop, at the signe of the Pide Bull, neere S. Austins Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The wonderfull deliuerance of the Iacob of Bristow.</note>
                  <note>A different work from STC 20769--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Naval battles --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20426:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20426:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION Strange and true, OF A SHIP OF <hi>BRISTOL</hi> named
the <hi>Jacob,</hi> of 120. Tunnes, which was about the end of Octob. laſt
1621. taken by the Turkiſh Pirats of ARGIER.</p>
            <p>And how within fiue dayes after, foure Engliſh Youths did
valiantly ouercome 13. of <hi>the ſaid Turks, and brought the Ship to</hi> S.
LVCAS <hi>in</hi> SPAINE, <hi>where they ſold nine of the Turks for
Gally-ſlaues.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>three-masted ship in full sail</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Butter,</hi> and are to be
ſold at his ſhop, at the ſigne of the Pide Bull neere <hi>S.
Auſtins</hi> Gate. 1622</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20426:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:20426:2"/>
            <head>A STRANGE AND TRVE RELATION of a Ship of BRISTOL named the
IACOB, <hi>of</hi> 120. <hi>Tunnes, which</hi> was about the end of Octob.
laſt 1621. taken by the Turkiſh Pirates of <hi>Argier:</hi> and how within
fiue dayes after, foure Engliſh Youths did <hi>valiantly ouercome thirteene
of the ſaid Turkes, and brought the Ship to</hi> SAINT LVCAS <hi>in</hi>
SPAINE, <hi>where they ſold nine of the</hi> TVRKES <hi>for
Galley-ſlaues.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S all Relations of any goodneſſe that befals to men, or of
any euill that they are defended or deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from, are manifeſt
declarations of Gods power in mans weaknes, and the richneſſe of the
Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties mercy gratiouſly extended to our pouertie and miſerie, wherein
from time to time <pb facs="tcp:20426:3"/>in all ages the
omnipotencie of the Creator hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and regarded the impotencie of his
creatures, thereby to ſtirre vs vp to the loue, feare and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his
eternall Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Omitting therefore to fill vp this diſcourſe with many old
examples, or to delay the Readers expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with impertinent ſtuffe, I
will here relate briefly and in ſuccinct and plaine manner, the ſtrange and
true deliuerance of a ſhip and foure Engliſh Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: in which report I
doubt not, but God will be glorified, and thoſe that reade or heare it well
ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Neere the latter end of October laſt, 1621. a ſhip belonging
to the Citie of <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> being about the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of 120. Tunnes,
was met withall and ſet vpon by Turkes or Pirats of <hi>Argier,</hi> where
after a long and ſharpe fight (being in the mouth of the Straits of
<hi>Gibraltar</hi>) the Engliſh ſhip being oppreſt with the multitude of
their enemies, was taken, their Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Cables, Anchors, Sailes, Ship and
men pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag'd, ranſack'd, and at the mercy of the inſulting Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians,
who to make their worke the ſurer, tooke all the Engliſhmen out of the
ſhip, except foure youthes, whoſe names were <hi>Iohn Cooke, William Ling,
Dauid Iones,</hi> and <hi>Robert Tuckey,</hi> into which ſhip the Turkes did
put thirteene of their owne men to command the Engliſh, and to bring the
ſhip as a prize to <hi>Argier;</hi> amongſt which one of the Pirats was
appointed Captaine, being a ſtrong, able, ſterne, and reſolute
fellow.</p>
            <p>Theſe foure poore youthes being thus fallen into the hands of
mercileſſe Infidels, began to ſtudie and <pb facs="tcp:20426:3"/>complot
all the meanes they could for the obtaining of their freedomes: Firſt they
conſidered the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and miſerable eſtates that they were like to
be in, as to be debard for euer from ſeeing their friends and Countrey, to be
chained, beaten, made ſlaues, and to eat the bread of affliction in the
Galleyes all the remainder of their vnfortunate liues, to haue their heads
ſhauen, to feed on courſe diet, to haue hard boords for beds, and which was
worſt of all, neuer to be partakers of the heauenly word and Sacraments.
Theſe and the like heauie and ſad cogitations were like ſo many
whetſtones to ſharpen their wits, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe meanes for their
deliuerance, and withall their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate caſes were ſpurres to rowſe
their courages to attempt any dangerous exploit for their enlargement, for they
did conſider wiſely that death was better then bondage, and that noble
reſolutions were the begetters or fore-runners of worthy actions, which made
them reſolue rather then they would ſuffer a ſlauiſh life, to trie the
hazard of a memorable death.</p>
            <p>Thus being quite hopeleſſe, hapleſſe, and for any thing
they knew, for euer helpleſſe, they ſailed fiue dayes and nights vnder
the command of the Pirates, when on the fift night, God in his great mercy
ſhewed them a meanes for their wiſhed-for eſcape, for in the dead of the
night the winde began to riſe, and in ſhort ſpace it blew ſo ſtiffe
that they were enforced to ſtrike both their top ſailes; and at laſt it
encreaſed to ſuch a guſt or ſtorme, that they muſt take in their
maine Saile, and being vnable to doe it themſelues, <hi>Iohn Cooke</hi> and
<hi>William Ling</hi> did call to the <hi>Turks</hi> for helpe: whereupon the
Captaine himſelfe came to help them; <pb facs="tcp:20426:4"/>who
ſtanding by the ſhips ſide, betweene the aforeſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> and
<hi>Dauid Iones,</hi> lending his hand to hale in the ſaile, the ſaid
<hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> ſuddenly tooke him by the breech and threw
him ouer boord, but by fortune he fell into the bunt of the ſaile, where
quickly catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold of a rope, hee (being a very ſtrong man) had almoſt
gotten into the ſhip againe: which <hi>Iohn Cooke</hi> perceiuing, leaped
ſpeedily to the Pumpe, and tooke off the Pumpe brake or handle, and caſt it
to <hi>William Ling,</hi> bidding him knocke him downe, which he was not long
in doing, but lifting vp the woodden weapon hee gaue him ſuch a palt on the
pate, as made his braines forſake the poſſeſſion of his head, with
which his body fell into the Sea.</p>
            <p>An Obiection may be made heere, why the <hi>Turke</hi> cried not
to his fellowes at firſt for helpe, or how theſe things could be done but
the reſt of his company muſt either ſee or heare it: to which I anſwer,
that at Sea a Guſt, Flaw, or Storme, hath many times a louder voice then a
man; beſides when Mariners doe hale or pull any thing, they doe make a
noyſe, as it were crying <hi>ha woet hale men hale,</hi> which with the
noyſe of the wind whizzing and hizzing in the ſhrowdes and cordage, would
ouercome and drowne the voice or crie of any man whatſoeuer. Beſides, his
companions were all buſie, ſome at the mizen, ſome at the
ſprit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, ſome to trim the fore-ſaile, and the night excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
darke, all theſe things concurring, and chiefly God graciouſly
aſſiſting, thus theſe braue Lads be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the buſineſſe
luckily.</p>
            <p>Nor muſt I forget <hi>Robert Tuckey,</hi> who was imployd all
this while in a place of maine importance, for hee <pb facs="tcp:20426:4"/>ſtood
at the Helme, and in all the weather guided the ſhip; now after the Captaine
was thus caſhierd, <hi>Iohn Cooke</hi> ran haſtily vp the halfe decke to
the Maſters Cabbin, neere which were ſtanding ſix or ſeuen Turks, but
hee being nothing daunted or diſcouraged for them, ſlipt roughly by them,
and gat out two good cuttleaxes, or ſhort ſwords, one of which he deliuered
to <hi>William Ling,</hi> withall ſaying, Courage my fellowes and countrey
men, God ſtrengthen and aſſiſt vs; with that they laid about them ſo
manfully, that they droue the Turkes from place to place in the ſhip, and
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing courſed them from the Poope to the Forecaſtle, they there valiantly
killed two of them, and gaue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a dangerous wound or two, who to eſcape
the further fury of their ſwords, leap't ſuddenly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord to goe ſeeke
his Captaine. Thus foure of the thirteene Turkes being made ſure for doing
any harme, they chaſed and followed the other nine ſo cloſe, that they
(to ſaue themſelues) being alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them ſore hurt and wounded,
ran betweene the ſhips decks; whereupon the Engliſh men faſtned the decks
to keepe them vnder: the Turkes, not knowing how to be reuenged, ran aftward
toward the helme, and vnſhipt their whipſtaffe, or as ſome call it a
whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocke, (which is the ſtaffe that a Mariner holds in his hand, when
hee guides or ſteeres a ſhip) by which meanes the Engliſh men were in
ſome diſtreſſe, by reaſon the ſhip lay tumbling and rowling
vnguided in the raging and boyſtrous billowes of the Sea: at laſt <hi>Iohn
Cooke</hi> and <hi>William Ling</hi> got each of them a Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, which they
quickly charged, and went downe where the nine Turkes were, making offers to
ſhoote <pb facs="tcp:20426:5"/>at them, at which they were
much terrified; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they quickly ſhip'd their whipſtocke againe,
deliuering the helme to <hi>Robert Tuckey,</hi> and then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently they
ſtowed all the Turkes vnder the hatches, where they kept them cloſe till
the next morning, and then as they had occaſion to vſe them, they would
call vp two or three of them at a time, to hale and pull ſheetes, tacks,
braces, and boleins, to hoyſe and ſtrike ſayles, or any ſuch
neceſſary and laborious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, in all which the Engliſh made the
Turkes attend them, and directing their courſe for the Port of <hi>Saint
Lucas</hi> in Spaine, they in ſhort time (by Gods ayde) happily and ſafely
arriued at the ſaid Port, where they ſold the nine Turkes for
Gally-ſlaues, for a good ſumme of money, and as I thinke a great deale more
then they are worth.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I ſet downe a true relation and deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of
theſe mens Captiuity, and ioyfull deliuerance, in which the Reader may ſee
the inſtability of humane accidents, and that the ſupernall power and
proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath a ruling hand to diſpoſe all the purpoſes of men to his
owne glory, and the good of thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon him. For what expectation
of redreſſe or comfort could theſe diſtreſſed youths haue, they
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but foure in number, their enemies being their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and thirteene
to the dozzen, ſtrong, luſty, able, and mercileſſe Turkes: In the
reaſon of man, the poore mens caſe was deſperat and paſt recouery; but
ſee, Gods arme is not ſhortned, hee that ouercame <hi>Pharaoh</hi> with
Lice, Graſhoppers, Froggs, and Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillers, to make <hi>Gedeon</hi>
victorious with the breaking of Earthen Pitchers, to cauſe Foxes with
fire-brands to <pb facs="tcp:20426:5"/>conſume the Corne of
the <hi>Philiſtims;</hi> to make <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> kill a thouſand men,
with a ſilly Aſſes ſaw bone, to ſtrengthen <hi>Dauid</hi> (being but
a young Lad, and a Shepherd) that with his owne hands he ſlew a raging Lyon,
and a rauening Beare, and after that with a ſling and a ſtone, to conquer
and kill a mighty Gyant: Innumerable are the examples that I could recite in
this kinde, but they are ſo manifeſt and frequent, that with admiration and
adoration, our humane reaſon is ſtrooke blinde and dumbe, whil'ſt our
faith with thankfulneſſe ſhould aſcend to the author of our
hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
            <p>Nor can I forget to commend vnto memory the good and well
beſtowed courage of theſe foure young men, for as a wiſe man ſaid,
<hi>the talke of a ſouldier ought to hang vpon the point of his ſword,</hi>
and courage cannot iuſtly be called courage but where the cauſe is iuſt,
and their cauſe being good, they thought it more courage to dye free, then to
liue ſlaues, they contemned all dangers, they deſpiſed all miſeries,
and they with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude conquered their Conquerors: How many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected
ſlaues would haue ſate whining like whelpes, and like vaſſals haue put
their necks into the nooſe of perpetuall ſeruitude, crying onely, God
helpe, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer endeuouring to vſe the meanes that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them,
whilſt theſe braue ſparks and ſpirits, the darlings of valour, to their
owne long laſting fame and their countreys neuer dying honour, makes
<hi>Briſtoll</hi> famous, <hi>Britaine</hi> glorious, their reputations
pretious, and the Turkes contemptuous.</p>
            <p>Had <hi>Iohn Cooke</hi> beene ſome Collonell, Captaine, or
Commander, or <hi>William Ling,</hi> ſome nauigating <pb facs="tcp:20426:6"/>Lord,
or <hi>Dauid Iones</hi> ſome gentleman of land and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or had <hi>Robert
Tuckey</hi> beene one of fortunes mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, to haue had more mony then wit, or
more wealth then valour, oh what a triumphing had heere beene then, what rare
Muſes would haue toyld like Mules, to haue gallopt with their flattering
encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums, beyond the 32. points of the compaſſe; whilſt theſe 4 rich
caskets of home-ſpun valour and courage, haue no pen to publiſh their
deſerued commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, no inuention to emblazon their ſaltwater honour,
but the poore lines and labours of a freſhwater Poet.</p>
            <p>Nor doe I write this to the intent that any man ſhould
preſume that their owne ſtrengths, valour, or courage is ſufficient to
doe theſe or the like actions, for they are not ordinary, and therefore man
is but made the ordinary inſtrument of an extraordinary power, and hee that
ſhall attribute ſuch things as theſe to the arme of fleſh and bloud, is
forgetfull, ingratefull, and in a manner Atheiſticall.</p>
            <p>One <hi>Iohn Fox</hi> an expert Mariner, and a good appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
and ſufficient Gunner, was (in the raigne of <hi>Qu. Elizabeth</hi>) taken by
the Turkes, and kept eighteene yeeres in moſt miſerable bondage and
ſlauery, at the end of which time, he eſpied his opportunity, (and God
aſſiſting him withall) that he ſlew his keeper, and fled to the ſeas
ſide, where he found a Gally with one hundred and fifty captiue Chriſtians,
which he ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waying their Anchor ſet ſaile, and fell to worke like
men, and ſafely arriued in Spaine, by which meanes he freed himſelfe and a
number of poore ſoules from long and intolerable ſeruitude, after which the
ſaid <hi>Iohn Fox</hi> came into England, and the Queene (being
<pb facs="tcp:20426:6"/>rightly informed of his braue
exploit) did graciouſly entertaine him for her ſeruant, and allowed him a
yeerely penſion.</p>
            <p>Captaine <hi>Nicolls</hi> with a ſhip of London called the
<hi>Dolphin,</hi> fought a long and bloudy fight, with many of the Turkiſh
men of warre at one time, at which time he ſunke ſome of them, ſlew many
of their men, and hauing his owne ſhip exceedingly rent and torne with the
enemies great ſhot, yet at laſt it pleaſed God to deliuer him from them,
ſo that he ſafely arriued at home.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>William Malam</hi> of <hi>Rotherhith,</hi> within
theſe three yeeres was ſet vpon by theſe Rouers, and after a long fight,
being much hurt by the Ordnance of the Turkes, (the night comming on) which
made the fight to ceaſe, when the Generall of the Pirats paſt his word, and
bound it with an oath, that if <hi>M. Malam</hi> would come aboord his ſhip
all night, that he ſhould well and ſafely be ſet aboord againe his owne
ſhip the next morning, vpon which word and oath <hi>M. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam</hi> went
aboord the Turke and a Merchant with him; but firſt before hee went commanded
his Mate to watch his opportunity, and ſteale away with the ſhip in the
night if he could, which fell out as he wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whereby all the Merchants
goods were ſaued, and the ſhip ſafely arriued heere at London: but in the
morning, when the Turkes did perceiue the Engliſh ſhip was gone, then would
they haue put <hi>M. Malam</hi> and the Merchant that was with him to death,
where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he vrged him with his oath and promiſe, which was that he ſhould
come and goe ſafely, and that if a Chriſtian had made him or any man ſuch
a promiſe, <pb facs="tcp:20426:7"/>and bound it with a vow,
hee would haue kept his word. And that (for any thing he knew) his ſhip
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo dangerouſly hurt by them might bee ſunke in the night, and not
eſcaped away as he imagined. Now whilſt they were in this diſcourſe,
preſently came a ſaile in ſight, which afterwards they found to bee a
ſmall Scottiſh ſhip bound for England, whom the Turkes quickly tooke, and
pillag'd at their pleaſure, taking from them their Sailes, Cables, Anchors,
and all things neceſſary for their vſe or preſeruation, and hauing
rob'd and rifled the poore Scot in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, they put <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Malam</hi>
and the Merchant into her to try their fortunes, either to ſinke or ſwim,
but it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God they ſafely arriued in the weſt part of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,
where they came home by land ſad and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate becauſe they could
not heare any newes of the ſhip: but the ſame night that he came home,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore day there was happy tidings brought of the ſhips ſafe arriuall into
the riuer of Thames.</p>
            <p>All theſe things are true vpon mine owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and
theſe worthy Mariners that haue beene ſo deliuered, doe, and euer did,
attribute all the meanes of their deliuerance to the mighty hand of God; and
they are ſo far from taking any of theſe things to their owne prayſe or
glory, that ſome of them haue euer done their beſt to ſuppreſſe them
from being printed. But as it were a meere vanity to boaſt or brag, ſo I
hold it a great pitty, that either Gods mercies, or mans benefits receiued,
ſhould be concealed.</p>
            <p>Here is matter ſufficient related, to perſwade men that as
they ſhould not preſumptuouſly aſcribe Gods honour to themſelues,
ſo on the other ſide here are <pb facs="tcp:20426:7"/>maine
motiues and examples to keepe men from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire in their greateſt
diſtreſſes: for as you ſee heere when all mans helpe failed, then Gods
helpe preuailed, to whom alone, as it is due, bee aſcribed all the
honour.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
